Our lives depend
تعتمد حياتنا على
on a world we can't see.
العالم الذي لا نراه.
Think about your week so far.
فكر في أسبوعك.
Have you watched TV, used GPS,
هل شاهدت التلفاز أو استخدمت نظام التموضع العالمي
checked the weather or even ate a meal?
أو تفقدت الطقس أو حتى تناولت وجبة طعام؟
These many things that enable our daily lives
هذه الأمور العديدة التي تسهل حياتنا اليومية
rely either directly or indirectly
تعتمد بشكل مباشر أو غير مباشر
on satellites.
علي الأقمار الصناعية.
And while we often take for granted
وبينما نحن نعتبرها من المسلمات
the services that satellites provide us,
الخدمات التي توفرها لنا الأقمار الصناعية،
the satellites themselves deserve our attention
فإن تلك الأقمار نفسها تستوجب اهتمامنا
as they are leaving a lasting mark
نظرا لتأثيرها الواضح علينا
on the space they occupy.
في الفضاء حيث هي.
People around the world rely on satellite infrastructure every day
يعتمد الناس حول العالم على بنيتنا التحتية من الأقمار الصناعية
for information, entertainment and to communicate.
لنقل المعلومات والترفيه والتواصل.
There's agricultural and environmental monitoring,
وتستعمل بالمراقبة الزراعية والبيئية،
Internet connectivity, navigation.
والاتصال بالإنترنت والملاحة.
Satellites even play a role
بل إن الأقمار الصناعية تلعب دورا
in the operation of our financial and energy markets.
في العمليات المنجزة بالأسواق المالية والطاقة
But these satellites that we rely on
لكن تلك الأقمار التي نعتمد عليها
day in and day out
ليل نهار
have a finite life.
لها عمر افتراضي محدود.
They might run out of propellant,
ربما ينفذ منها الوقود
they could malfunction,
أو قد تتعطل
or they may just naturally reach the end of their mission life.
أو بكل بساطة قد تصل إلي نهاية مهمتها.
At this point, these satellites effectively become space junk,
عند هذه اللحظة، تصبح تلك الأقمار قمامة فضائية
cluttering the orbital environment.
تتراكم في البيئة الفضائية.
So imagine you're driving down the highway on a beautiful, sunny day
لذا، تخيلوا أنكم تقودون سيارتكم في الطريق السريع في يوم جميل مشمس
out running errands.
لقضاء بعض المشاوير.
You've got your music cranked,
والموسيقي تملأ السيارة
your windows rolled down,
والنوافذ مفتوحة
with the cool breeze blowing through your hair.
والنسيم العليل يداعب شعرك.
Feels nice, right?
إحساس رائع، أليس كذلك؟
Everything is going smoothly
كل شيء على خير ما يرام
until suddenly your car stutters and stalls
إلى أن توقفت سيارتكم فجأة
right in the middle of the highway.
في منتصف الطريق السريع.
So now you have no choice but to abandon your car
فكان لا بد عليكم التخلي عن سيارتكم
where it is on the highway.
بمكانها بمنتصف الطريق السريع.
Maybe you were lucky enough
ربما كنتم محظوظين كفاية
to be able to move it out of the way and into a shoulder lane
لتحركوها من منتصف الطريق وركنها جانباً
so that it's out of the way of other traffic.
بحيث لا تعرقل طريق السيارات الأخرى.
A couple of hours ago,
قبل بضع ساعات،
your car was a useful machine that you relied on in your everyday life.
كانت سيارتكم آلة مفيدة، تعتمدون عليها في حياتكم اليومية.
Now, it's a useless hunk of metal
والآن، هي مجرد كتلة معدنية بلا فائدة
taking up space in a valuable transportation network.
تشغل حيزا مهماً في شبكة النقل.
And imagine international roadways all cluttered with broken down vehicles
تخيلوا الآن طرق سريعة دولية تتكدس فيها جميع السيارات المعطلة
that are just getting in the way of other traffic.
التي تعترض طريق السيارات الأخرى.
And imagine the debris that would be strewn everywhere
تخيلوا حجم الأنقاض المنتشرة في كل مكان
if a collision actually happened,
لو حدث اصطدام،
thousands of smaller pieces of debris
الآلاف من الأجزاء الصغيرة من الأنقاض
becoming new obstacles.
ستصبح عقبات جديدة.
This is the paradigm of the satellite industry.
هذا مثال على صناعة الأقمار الصناعية
Satellites that are no longer working
الأقمار الصناعية التي ما عادت تعمل
are often left to deorbit over many, many years,
والتي تترك في العادة تهيم بالمدار للعديد من السنوات،
or only moved out of the way as a temporary solution.
أو تزاح من المسار كحل مؤقت.
And there are no international laws in space
ولا يوجد هناك قوانين دولية تنظم الفضاء
to enforce us to clean up after ourselves.
لتجبرنا على تنظيف مخلفاتنا.
So the world's first satellite, Sputnik I,
لذا، فإن أول قمر صناعي، سبوتنيك 1،
was launched in 1957,
أطلق سنة 1957،
and in that year, there were only a total of three launch attempts.
وفي تلك السنة، كان هناك فقط ثلاث محاولات إطلاق.
Decades later and dozens of countries from all around the world
وبعد عقود من الزمن أطلقت العديد من الدول حول العالم
have launched thousands of more satellites into orbit,
الآلاف من الأقمار الصناعية إلى المدار،
and the frequency of launches is only going to increase in the future,
وستستمر نسبة إطلاق الأقمار الصناعية في الارتفاع مستقبلا،
especially if you consider things like the possibility
خاصة إذا أخذتم في الاعتبار احتمالية
of 900-plus satellite constellations being launched.
أن أكثر من 900 قمر صناعي قد أطلق بالفعل.
Now, we send satellites to different orbits
الآن، نحن نطلق الأقمار لمدارات مختلفة
depending on what they're needed for.
اعتمادا على الحاجة منها.
One of the most common places we send satellites
وأحد أكثر المدارات التي نرسل إليها الأقمار
is the low Earth orbit,
هو المدار الأرضي المنخفض،
possibly to image the surface of Earth
على الأرجح لتصوير سطح الأرض
at up to about 2,000 kilometers altitude.
من على ارتفاع 2.000 كيلومتر.
Satellites there are naturally buffeted by Earth's atmosphere,
وبالطبع فإن الأقمار هناك تصطدم بالغلاف الجوي للأرض،
so their orbits naturally decay,
فيتغير بطبيعة الحال مدارها،
and they'll eventually burn up,
لتحترق في نهاية المطاف
probably within a couple of decades.
على الأرجح خلال بضعة عقود.
Another common place we send satellites
والمدار الثاني الذي نضع فيه الأقمار عادة
is the geostationary orbit
هو المدار الجغرافي الثابت
at about 35,000 kilometers altitude.
على ارتفاع 35.000 كيلومتر.
Satellites there remain in the same place above Earth as the Earth rotates,
حيث تبقى الأقمار في مدار ثابت حول الأرض أثناء دورانها،
which enables things like communications or television broadcast, for example.
وهو ما يسمح بالاتصال ونقل البث التلفزيوني.
Satellites in high orbits like these could remain there for centuries.
ويمكن للأقمار في تلك المدارات العالية أن تبقى هناك لقرون.
And then there's the orbit coined "the graveyard,"
كما أنه هناك المدار المعروف "بالمقبرة"
the ominous junk or disposal orbits,
النفايات المهجورة أو مدارات الخردة،
where some satellites are intentionally placed
حيث توضع بعض الأقمار عن عمد
at the end of their life
في انتظار نهاية حياتها
so that they're out of the way of common operational orbits.
لكي لا تعرقل المدارات التشغيلية المشتركة.
Of the nearly 7,000 satellites launched since the late 1950s,
من بين ما يقارب 7.000 قمرا صناعيا أطلق منذ الخمسينيات
only about one in seven is currently operational,
فقط واحد من كل سبعة ما زال يشتغل حاليا،
and in addition to the satellites that are no longer working,
وبالإضافة إلى الأقمار المتوقفة عن العمل،
there's also hundreds of thousands of marble-sized debris
يوجد مئات الآلاف من الحطام بحجم البلي الصغيرة
and millions of paint chip-sized debris
والملايين من الحطام بحجم رقائق الدهان
that are also orbiting around the Earth.
تدور أيضا حول الأرض.
Space debris is a major risk to space missions,
وتشكل تلك المخلفات تهديدا كبيرا للرحلات الفضائية،
but also to the satellites that we rely on each and every day.
وكذا على الأقمار التي نطلقها كل يوم.
Now, because space debris and junk has become increasingly worrisome,
ولكون حجم الحطام الفضائي والمخلفات أصبح أكثر إقلاقا،
there have been some national and international efforts
كانت هناك بعض الجهود الوطنية والدولية
to develop technical standards
لتطوير معايير تقنية
to help us limit the generation of additional debris.
لتساعدنا على الحد من إنتاج المزيد من الحطام.
So for example, there are recommendations
وعلى سبيل المثال، هناك معايير
for those low-Earth orbiting spacecraft
للمركبات التي تدور بمدارات منخفضة حول الأرض
to be made to deorbit in under 25 years,
لتسحب من مدارها قبل 25 سنة،
but that's still a really long time,
مع ذلك ما زالت تلك المدة طويلة جدا،
especially if a satellite hasn't been working for years.
خاصة إذا كان القمر متوقفًا عن العمل منذ سنوات.
There's also mandates for those dead geostationary spacecraft
كما أن هناك عرائض لإبعاد المركبات الفضائية المهجورة
to be moved into a graveyard orbit.
إلى مدار مقبرة.
But neither of these guidelines is binding under international law,
لكن هذه القواعد ليست ملزمة بموجب القانون الدولي،
and the understanding is that they will be implemented through national mechanisms.
وإذا علمنا أنه سيتوجب تفعيلها بآليات وطنية خاصة بكل دولة.
These guidelines are also not long-term,
فإن تلك القواعد أيضا غير مجدية على المدى الطويل،
they're not proactive,
وليست استباقية،
nor do they address the debris that's already up there.
ولا تراعي الحطام المتواجد أصلا هناك.
They're only in place to limit the future creation of debris.
بل وضعت فقط للحد من إنتاج المزيد من الحطام مستقبلا.
Space junk is no one's responsibility.
النفايات الفضائية ليست مسؤولية جهة واحدة بمفردها.
Now, Mount Everest is actually an interesting comparison
الحقيقة أن جبل إفرست هو مقارنة مثيرة للاهتمام
of a new approach to how we interact with our environments,
بالنسبة لمقاربة جديدة حول كيفية تفاعلنا مع بيئتنا،
as it's often given the dubious honor
بما أنه منح الشرف المشكوك فيه
of being the world's highest garbage dump.
بكونه أعلى مكب نفايات في العالم.
Decades after the first conquest of the world's highest peak,
بعد عقود من أول غزو لأعلى قمة في العالم،
tons of rubbish left behind by climbers
بدأت أطنان المخلفات التي تركها المتسلقون خلفهم
has started to raise concern,
تثير القلق.
and you may have read in the news that there's speculation
وقد تكونوا قرأتم في الجرائد بأن هناك أحاديث
that Nepal will crack down on mountaineers
بأن دولة نيبال ستفرض على المتسلقين
with stricter enforcement of penalties and legal obligations.
عقوبات وضوابط قانونية صارمة.
The goal, of course, is to persuade climbers
والهدف بالطبع هو حث المتسلقين
to clean up after themselves,
على تنظيف مخلفاتهم،
so maybe local not-for-profits will pay climbers who bring down extra waste,
وربما ستدفع المنظمات غير الربحية للمتسلقين لتنظيف بعض المخلفات الإضافية
or expeditions might organize voluntary cleanup trips.
أو قد تنظم حملات تطوعية كرحلات تنظيفية.
And yet still many climbers feel
ومع ذلك ما زال العديد من المتسلقين يشعرون
that independent groups should police themselves.
بأنه على المجموعات المستقلة مراقبة بعضها البعض.
There's no simple or easy answer,
لا يوجد جواب بسيط أو سهل.
and even well-intentioned efforts at conservation
حتى جهود الحميدة المبذولة في الحفاظ على البيئة
often run into problems.
تواجه في العادة مشاكل تعرقلها.
But that doesn't mean we shouldn't do everything in our power
لكن هذا لا يعني، أنه لا يجب أن نبذل كل ما نستطيع
to protect the environments that we rely and depend on,
لحماية البيئة التي نعتمد عليها،
and like Everest, the remote location and inadequate infrastructure
كما الحال مع افرست، فإن بعد الموقع وعدم ملائمة البنية التحتية
of the orbital environment
مع البيئة المدارية
make waste disposal a challenging problem.
تجعل من المخلفات المتراكمة مشكلة مستعصية.
But we simply cannot reach new heights
وببساطة لا يمكننا بلوغ مستوى جديد أعلى
and create an even higher garbage dump,
وإنشاء مكب نفايات أكثر علو،
one that's out of this world.
هناك خارج حدود هذا العالم.
The reality of space
الحقيقة في الفضاء
is that if a component on a satellite breaks down,
أنه إذا أصيب جزء من القمر الصناعي بعطب ما
there really are limited opportunities for repairs,
فإن إمكانيات إصلاحه محدودة للغاية
and only at great cost.
وبتكلفة باهظة.
But what if we were smarter about how we designed satellites?
لكن ماذا لو كنا أذكى في طريقة تصميمنا للأقمار الصناعية؟
What if all satellites,
ماذا لو قمنا بتصميمها،
regardless of what country they were built in,
بغض النظر عن الدولة المصنعة لها،
had to be standardized in some way
بشكل ما لتلائم شروط معيارية
for recycling, servicing
لإعادة التدوير أو التصليح
or active deorbiting?
أو الإخراج النشط من المدار؟
What if there actually were international laws with teeth
ماذا لو كانت هناك قوانين دولية صارمة
that enforced end-of-life disposal of satellites
تنص على إعادة تدوير الأقمار الصناعية بنهاية عمرها الافتراضي
instead of moving them out of the way
بدل الإكتفاء بإزالتها من الطريق
as a temporary solution?
كحل مؤقت؟
Or maybe satellite manufacturers need to be charged a deposit
أو ربما على المصنعين دفع وديعة مالية
to even launch a satellite into orbit,
قبل إطلاق أقمارهم نحو المدار،
and that deposit would only be returned
شريطة إرجاع تلك الوديعة
if the satellite was disposed of properly
فقط إذا أعيد تدوير القمر بالشكل الملائم
or if they cleaned up some quota of debris.
أو إذا قاموا بتنظيف حصة محددة من الحطام.
Or maybe a satellite needs to have technology on board
أو ربما يجب على القمر أن يحتوي على تقنية
to help accelerate deorbit.
تسرع من عملية إخراجه من المدار.
There are some encouraging signs.
هناك بعض الإشارات المشجعة.
The UK's TechDemoSat-1, launched in 2014, for example,
فالقمر البريطاني، تيك-ديموسات-1، الذي أطلق في 2014، على سبيل المثال،
was designed for end-of-life disposal
صمم ليعاد تدويره بنهاية عمره الافتراضي
via a small drag sail.
بواسطة شراع مقاومة صغير.
This works for the satellite because it's small,
ولقد نجح الأمر مع ذلك القمر لكونه صغير الحجم،
but satellites that are higher or in larger orbits
لكن بالنسبة للأقمار المتواجدة على ارتفاع أعلى أو في مدارات أكبر
or are larger altogether, like the size of school buses,
أو التي يفوق حجمها حجم باص مدرسي.
will require other disposal options.
ستحتاج وسائل أخرى لإعادة تدويرها.
So maybe you get into things like high-powered lasers
وبالتالي ربما عليكم التركيز على تقنية الليزر الشديد القوة،
or tugging using nets or tethers,
أو القطر بواسطة الشبكات أو الحبال،
as crazy as those sound in the short term.
رغم كون الأمر قد يبدو مجنونا على المدى القريب.
And then one really cool possibility
الإمكانية الأخرى المثيرة بالفعل
is the idea of orbital tow trucks or space mechanics.
هي فكرة شاحنات القطر المدارية أو ميكانيكا الفضاء.
Imagine if a robotic arm
تخيلوا لو كان بإمكان ذراع آلية
on some sort of space tow truck
لنوع من شاحنات القطر الفضائي
could fix the broken components on a satellite,
إصلاح الأجزاء المعطلة في القمر الاصطناعي،
making them usable again.
لتعيدها مرة أخرى إلى العمل.
Or what if that very same robotic arm
أو ماذا إن كان بإمكان نفس الذراع الآلية
could refuel the propellant tank on a spacecraft
تزويد الوقود الدفعي لخزان مركبة فضائية
that relies on chemical propulsion
تعمل بنظام الدفع الكميائي
just like you or I would refuel the fuel tanks on our cars?
كما لو كنا سنزود خزانات السيارات بالوقود؟
Robotic repair and maintenance
يمكن لآلات الإصلاح والصيانة
could extend the lives of hundreds of satellites orbiting around the Earth.
تمديد الأعمار الافتراضية لمئات الأقمار الدائرة حول الأرض.
Whatever the disposal or cleanup options we come up with,
بغض النظر عن أفكار إعادة التدوير أو التنظيف التي نأتي بها،
it's clearly not just a technical problem.
فمن الواضح أن الأمر ليس مجرد مشكل تقني.
There's also complex space laws and politics that we have to sort out.
هناك أيضا قوانين وسياسات فضاء معقدة يجب علينا تنسيقها.
Simply put, we haven't found a way to use space sustainably yet.
باختصار، مازلنا لم نعثر على طريقة لاستخدام الفضاء بشكل مستدام.
Exploring, innovating to change the way we live and work
الاستكشاف والابتكار لتغيير طريقة العيش والعمل
are what we as humans do,
هو ما نقوم به كبشر،
and in space exploration,
وفي استكشاف الفضاء،
we're literally moving beyond the boundaries of Earth.
نحن نتخطى حرفيا حدود الأرض.
But as we push thresholds in the name of learning and innovation,
لكننا بتخطي الحدود باسم التعلم والابتكار
we must remember that accountability for our environments never goes away.
علينا أن نتذكر بأن المسؤولية على بيئتنا لا تسقط أبدا.
There is without doubt congestion in the low Earth and geostationary orbits,
إن المدارات الأرضية المنخفضة والجغرافية الثابتة مكتظة بدون شك،
and we cannot keep launching new satellites
ولا يمكننا الاستمرار في إطلاق أقمار جديدة
to replace the ones that have broken down
لتحل محل تلك المعطلة
without doing something about them first,
دون إيجاد حل لها أولا،
just like we would never leave a broken down car
مثلما كنا لنفعل لسيارة معطلة
in the middle of the highway.
في وسط الطريق السريع.
Next time you use your phone,
عند استعمالكم للهاتف مستقبلا
check the weather or use your GPS,
أو التحقق من الطقس أو استعمالكم نظام التموضع العالمي،
think about the satellite technologies that make those activities possible.
تفكروا في الأقمار التي جعلت تلك الأعمال اليومية أمرا ممكنا.
But also think about the very impact
لكن أيضا تفكروا في الأثر
that the satellites have on the environment surrounding Earth,
الذي تتركه الأقمار على البيئة المحيطة بالأرض،
and help spread the message that together we must reduce our impact.
وساعدوا على نشر الرسالة، بأنه علينا معا خفض تأثيرنا.
Earth orbit is breathtakingly beautiful
المدار الأرضي جميل بصورة اخّاذة
and our gateway to exploration.
وهو بوابتنا نحو الاستكشاف.
It's up to us to keep it that way.
والأمر عائد إلينا بأن نبقي عليه بهذا الشكل.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)